A Guide to the The Papers of Nathaniel Hawthorne, 1813-1904, n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
The Papers of Nathaniel Hawthorne, 1813-1904, n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
6249, -a, -b, -c, -d, -e, -f, -g, -h
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Scope and Content
The Papers of Nathaniel Hawthorne consist of correspondence, literary manuscripts, and other papers. The material pertains to Hawthorne's days at the customhouse in Boston (1839-1840), in the District of Salem and Beverly (1847-1854), and as consul at Liverpool (1853-1860).
The papers include family correspondence and letters to publishers; a few early papers of Hawthorne's ancestors; a photocopy of the original manuscript of A Wonder Book for Girls and Boys (1852); and, manuscripts of the shorter sketches Consular experiences and Jonathan Cilley, and of other works.
Correspondents and persons mentioned include William Cox Bennett, Francis Bennoch, Zachariah Burchmore, Moncure Conway, E. A. Duyckinck, Lydia T. Fessenden, James T. Fields, Samuel G. Goodrich, Rufus W. Griswold, Elizabeth Manning Hawthorne, Julian Hawthorne, Sophia Amelia Peabody Hawthorne, Una Hawthorne, George S. Hilliard, Ethan Allen Hitchcock, A[lexander?] Ireland, George Payne Rainsford James, George Parsons Lathrop, Henry W. Longfellow, Herman Melville, Samuel Longfellow, Horace Mann, Horace Mann, Jr., James Miller, John L. O'Sullivan, Elizabeth Palmer Peabody, Franklin Pierce, Stephen Pleasonton, Roberts Brothers, George Nicholas Sanders, William Buell Sprague, Charles Sumner, Ticknor and Co., William A. Tiffany, Martin Van Buren, and C.W. Webber.
The collection also includes a volume of tributes by American authors on the 100th anniversary of Hawthorne's birth.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged in four series. Series I: Literary Manuscripts is arranged alphabetically by title. Series II: Letters By and Related to Nathaniel Hawthorne consists of Subseries A: Dated Letters and Subseries B: Undated Letters. Series III: Miscellaneous Manuscripts is arranged chronologically. Series IV: Photographs and Prints is arranged by subject.
Contents List
- Series I: Literary Manuscripts
  - The Blithedale Romance by Nathaniel Hawthorne, 1852, Photocopy from original manuscript in the Pierpont Morgan Library; includes ALS from Nathaniel Hawthorne to "Dear Whipple," 1852 May 2, 2 pp. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Asks for comments on the manuscript and help choosing a title. #6249-i.
  - Chiefly about War Matters by a Peaceable Man [Nathaniel Hawthorne], AMsS, 36 pp. on 20 l.; with autograph corrections. (Box-folder 1:2)
    With an ANS by Robert Collyer, n.d.; a lithograph portrait of Hawthorne; and an engraved view of Hawthorne's house in Concord, Mass., all loose in a leather and cloth binding. #6249-g.
  - Consular Experiences by Nathaniel Hawthorne, [ca. 1862], AMs, 39 pp. on 20 l.; with autograph corrections and a clipped signature affixed at the end. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Bound in full black roan, titled in gilt. #6249-a.
  - [Copy book] Nathaniel Hawthorne, [ca. 1815], AMsS, 21 pp. on 11 l., oblong 8vo. in blue-gray wrappers, "Nath. Hawthorne" inscribed on the cover, also signed on the last page; with typed dealer's description, 1 p.; in blue morocco-backed cloth slipcase and chemise, bearing the leather book label of E.H. Mills. SLIPCASE. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Penmanship exercises. #6249-a.
  - A Description of a Tragedy, which happened at the Notch of the White Hills, in N.H. on Monday the 28th day of August 1826, by H. Aldrich, 1826 September 18, Photocopy of AMsS, 2 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Describes a violent rain storm there on that date during which a great landslide buried a family of nine and closes with observations about the uncertainty of life. #6249-h.
  - I passed by the Old Manse... [by Nathaniel Hawthorne], 1852 July 15, AMs, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:5)
    Essay for Homes of American Authors. #6249-b.
  - Jonathan Cilley by Nathaniel Hawthorne, 1838 April 19, AMs, 10 pp.; with ALS, Nathaniel Hawthorne to [J.L.] O'Sullivan, 1838 April 19, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:6)
    Profile of New Hampshire Congressman J. Cilley, summarizing his career and circumstances of his death in a duel with Kentucky Congressman Graves, accompanied by the letter, conveying it to O'Sullivan for publication. #6249-a.
  - Our Old Home, [by Nathaniel Hawthorne], [1863?], 2 leaves. AMs fragment, 3 pp. (numbered 25-27) on 2 l. with autograph corrections. (Box-folder 1:7)
    Description of England's Warwick area, annotated on the blank verso of the second leaf: A leaf from Hawthorne, Our Old Home, J.T. Field.
  - Septimus Felton, a leaf, [by Nathaniel Hawthorne], [1872?], AMs fragment, 2 pp. (numbered 67-68) on 1 l.; with autograph corrections. (Box-folder 1:8)
    #6249-a.
  - A Sketch or Two in Warwick [by Nathaniel Hawthorne], n.d., AMs, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with autograph corrections. (Box-folder 1:9)
    #6249-e.
  - Times Portraiture fragment, [by Nathaniel Hawthorne], 1838, AMs fragment, 2 clipped pieces, with small envelope annotated by Elizabeth P. Peabody. (Box-folder 1:10)
    Miss Peabody identified the fragment as cut from Nathaniel Hawthorne's manuscript of a New Year's Day article for the carrier of the Salem Gazette. #6249-a.
  - A Wonder Book for Girls and Boys by Nathaniel Hawthorne, 1851, AMS (photocopy), bound. Transferred from the Papers of Fredson Bowers (MSS 12730, Box 10). (Box-folder 1:11)
    Bound volume. #12730.
  - Cuban Journal by Sophia Peabody, 1838 December 6, AMsS, 18 pp. on 9 l., preceded by her ALS to Nathaniel Hawthorne, 1 p. on 1 l., all stitched together. (Box-folder 1:12)
    Presentation letter is a foreword recalling Hawthorne's pleasure in receiving an earlier account of her Cuban sojourn and offering this continuation. With a typed transcript, imperfect, omitting some text, 8 pp. #6249-a.
- Series II: Letters by and Related to Nathaniel Hawthorne
  - Subseries A: Dated Letters
    - Nathaniel Hawthorne to Dear Uncle [Robert Manning], 1813 December 9, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l., with envelope addressed to Richard C. Manning, Esq., and typed transcript and photocopy. (Box-folder 1:13)
      Has not been improving from a foot injury that has kept him out of school for four weeks, while Louisa has recovered from her ailment and returned to school; asks after his uncle and Richard. #6249-a.
    - N[athaniel] Hawthorne to "Dear Uncle" [Robert Manning], 1820 August 15, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l., with attached address leaf, with typed transcript. (Box-folder 1:14)
      Received letter from mother as well as three periodicals (Analectic, Gazette, and Register). Expects ship to sail soon carrying one dog and describes another dog's health problems. #6249-a.
    - Nath[anie]l Hawthorne to "Dear Uncle" [Robert Manning], 1820 September 12, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l., addressed on the verso. (Box-folder 1:15)
      Observes that his uncle's recent letter from Raymond, Maine, did not mention if the dog arrived there and that it did describe the place so negatively that he fears selling his land there will go poorly. #6249-a.
    - Nath[aniel] Hawthorne to Samuel G. Goodrich, 1829 December 20, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l., with attached address leaf and photocopy. (Box-folder 1:16)
      Thanks Goodrich for reading his literary submissions, although still doubting prospects for their acceptance, and describes progress writing various additional tales, one based on local superstitions. #6249-a.
    - Nath[aniel] Hawthorne to [Elizabeth Hawthorne], 1836 March 17, ANS, 1 p. on 1 l., with typed transcript. (Box-folder 1:17)
      Requires her Hamilton submission and any other pieces for impending publication in "the May number." #6249-a.
    - Nath[aniel] Hawthorne to Mrs. L[ydia]T[uttle] Fessenden, 1838 April 12, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l., with a typed transcript and with 2 TLsS from Norman N. Pearson to Carroll A. Wilson, 10 September and 7 October 1935. (Box-folder 1:18)
      About letters loaned for the published edition, about the significance to Hawthorne of their recipients, especially, Mrs. Fessenden, and of the implications of some of his comments.
      Desires to visit her at home before she moves away from Boston. For himself has nearly abandoned the idea of going to Washington, but after an unproductive winter in Salem rather than Boston, which she had advised, plans spending the summer in the country somewhere. His mother and sister Louisa are not well. #6249-a.
    - Nath[aniel] Hawthorne to Catharine, Miss C.C. Ainsworth, 1838 April 12, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l., addressed on the verso to Mrs. Lydia T. Fessenden. (Box-folder 1:19)
      Uses a teasing tone to complain that he would never write again were it not his profession and thanks her for ceasing her request that he write a story for her alone. Thinks "Miss Augusta" should return home from her travels. Has heard that he himself is engaged to two ladies, which is news to him, and hopes the rumors will not have him married unawares. Begs her wise indulgence of his banter. #6249-a.
    - Nathaniel Hawthorne to George Bancroft, 1839 January 11, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l. with integral address leaf. (Box-folder 1:20)
      Accepts with thanks Bancroft's offer of a position in the custom house inspector's department, about which he has sought advice from Gen. McNeel and Mr. Jameson, and would prefer the ordinary inspector's duties to one of greater responsibility. Expects to move to Boston within a few weeks and would like to begin work then. #6249-a.
    - Nath[aniel] Hawthorne to B.B. Thacher, 1839 May 15, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. with integral address leaf, inlaid in a larger leaf; with 1 penciled forgery of the letter, 1 p. on 1 l., and a typed transcript. (Box-folder 1:21)
      After delaying, wishes to arrange a meeting to present a copy of his Tales and greet personally a fellow Bowdoin alumnus. #6249-a.
    - [Nathaniel Hawthorne] to "Dearest Dove," Sophia A. Peabody, 1840 April 30, AL fragment, 3 pp., 1 l. folded with portions cut away; with TLS, George S. Hellman to W.K. Bixby, 1908 February 14, 1 p. on 1 l., with typed transcript, 2 pp. (2 copies) and a photocopy. (Box-folder 1:22)
      Responding to a letter just received, he expresses loving concern for her and reports his weariness after a long day's work for the customs house. #6249-a.
    - Nath[aniel Hawthorne] to [George S.] Hillard, 1841 July 16, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:23)
      Regrets failing to write a promised story, now past deadline and not to be done; life and duties at Brook Farm both rest and work him too hard so that he cannot concentrate on writing stories, which "grow like vegetables, and are not manufactured, like a fine table." #6249-a.
    - S.G. Goodrich to Revd. W.B. Sprague, 1845 June 4, ALS, 2 pp. with integral address leaf on 1 l., folded. (Box-folder 1:24)
      Goodrich, who had published a number of Hawthorne's tales, forwards additional volumes of Parley's Cabinet Library to Sprague and requests an endorsement of the series for adoption by New York's state school library. #6249-a.
    - Nath[anie]l Hawthorne to Gen. James Miller, 1848 February 1 and March 1, 2 ALsS, each 1 p. on 1 l., the first with envelope, the second with integral address leaf; with typed transcripts. (Box-folder 1:25)
      They report the absence due to injury of Permanent Inspector William R. Lee and the expense of temporary inspectors. #6249-a.
    - Nathaniel Hawthorne to Gen. James Miller, 1848 April 15, ALS, 1 p. with integral address leaf on 1 l. folded; with typed transcript. (Box-folder 1:26)
      Asks the collector of customs whether to investigate the Schooner Stirling, claimed to be from Boston, bound for Bangor, but suspected to be from the West Indies with original cargo. #6249-a.
    - Nath[anie]l Hawthorne to Gen. James Miller, 1848 November 13, ALS, 1 p. with integral address leaf, on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:27)
      Informs the collector of customs that Capt. William Josser (?), a revenue boatman, has been long out due to injury, which has proven to be permanent, and suggests his removal from the payroll. #6249-a.
    - Nath[anie]l Hawthorne to E. P. Whipple, 1848 December 6, ALS, 1 p. with integral address leaf, on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:28)
      Arranging speakers for the lyceum, he advises that Prof. Agassiz will speak in December and that Whipple could be scheduled for 3 January if that would suit him. #6249-a.
    - Nath[anie]l Hawthorne to "Sir," 1849 January 1, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:29)
      Making a plea for retention of an experienced and valuable Salem Customs House clerk, Zachariah Burchmore, Jr., whose position there was reported to be threatened. #6249-a.
    - Nath[anie]l Hawthorne to Charles Sumner, 1849 January 8, ALS, with integral address leaf, on 1 l. folded. (Box-folder 1:30)
      Briefly confirming January 24 for Mr. Sumner's visit (to give a lyceum lecture). #6249-a.
    - Nath[anie]l Hawthorne to "Dear Sir" [Henry Colman], 1849 January 15, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l., with typed transcript. (Box-folder 1:31)
      Expressing the lyceum managers' interest in having both Mr. Colman's lectures and explaining schedule possibilities for their delivery. #6249-a.
    - Nath[anie]l Hawthorne to [Samuel?] Longfellow, 1849 June 19, ALS, 1 p., with integral blank, 1 l. folded; with TLS, Harry Dana to Wilson, 1941 October 21, 1 p. on 1 l., concerning the letter's provenance and the Hawthorne-Longfellow family relationships. (Box-folder 1:32)
      Reporting that a schedule conflict would prevent his visiting when proposed and claiming to be well despite the recent loss of his Customs House position, phrased as "my head has been chopt off." #6249-a.
    - Nath[anie]l Hawthorne to Horace Mann, 1849 July 2, ALS, 1 p., with integral address leaf, 1 l. folded; accompanied by a typed transcript and photostatic copy of NH's letter. (Box-folder 1:33)
      Having heard that some further charges concerning the Salem Customs House might be made against him by those with political motives, NH requests that, Mr. Mann, who had offered to assist, enquire about them so that NH might answer them in hope of reinstatement to his former position. #6249-a.
    - Nath[anie]l Hawthorne to [Charles Wilkins] Webber, 1849 December 18, ALS, 2 pp. with integral address leaf, on 1 l.; with typed transcript, 2 pp. (Box-folder 1:34)
      Requesting that Mr. Webber [American Review, editor] explain to the Museum editor, to whom he had given NH's Unpardonable Sin for publication, that the piece should appear only as an excerpt from his forthcoming book and only when that book appeared and NH confirmed it; also reporting on his wife's ill health and treatment. #6249-a.
    - Nath[anie[l Hawthorne to Zach[ariah Burchmore], 1850 June 9, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. folded. (Box-folder 1:35)
      Reports on his new home and life in Lenox, Massachusetts; on missing brandy, which he pledged to forgo, as well as other amenities not locally available; on his views of Pike, their fellow Salem Customs House employee, and of events there; and encourages continued correspondence and Burchmore's visiting him in Lenox. #6249-a.
    - Nath[anie]l Hawthorne to J.C. McGuire, 1850 September 17, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l., with a typed transcript, 1 p., and a photographic copy. (Box-folder 1:36)
      Thanking him for complements on his writings and responding as requested. #6249-a.
    - Nath[anie]l Hawthorne to [Elizabeth Peabody], [1850?], Postscript apparently from an ALS, with a clipped signature pasted in its lower margin, 1 p. on 1 l., inlaid in a slightly larger leaf. (Box-folder 1:37)
      Declines her request that he write for her an "'exhaustive criticism' of Grace Greenwood's works", which he doesn't think warrant it, suggesting that she herself undertake whatever she has in mind, and noting that his wife disapproves Greenwood's writing on moral grounds. #6249-a.
    - Nath[anie]l Hawthorne to "Dear Doctor" [Benjamin Browne], [1851] January 13, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:38)
      Sends partial payment on a debt, with thanks for help and patience. Notes general good health of the family, the blessings of his current situation, made possible by dismissal from the Salem Customs House position, and his intention to send the doctor a copy of his new book (House of the Seven Gables), soon to be published. #6249-a.
    - Nath[anie]l Hawthorne to Zach[ariah Burchmore], 1851 February 11, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. folded; with typed transcript and biographical sketch, 3 pp. (Box-folder 1:39)
      Sends money and asks that it be taken for payment of his outstanding Salem water bill. Sadly acknowledges death of Burchmore's father, asks that Z.B. distribute copies of his forthcoming book to Salem friends, describes the remoteness of his Berkshire home with its many confining tasks, and asks about the Burchmores' activities and political views. #6249-a.
    - Nath[anie]l Hawthorne to "Dear Sir," 1851 April 12, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l. folded; with typed transcript, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:40)
      Fulfilling a request for his autograph, sent late as he was loath to write. #6249-a.
    - Nath[anie]l Hawthorne to G.P.R. James, 1851 June 16, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l., inlaid in heavier paper; with typed transcript, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:41)
      Forwards a letter about "young ladies' compositions," which will be sent for G.P.R.J. to read. Welcomes him to the Berkshires and encourages an exchange of visits. #6249-a.
    - Nath[anie]l Hawthorne to Ticknor & Co., 1851 October 22, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l., laid down on heavy paper, on the verso of which are affixed clipped autographs of four others (one an ANS of Abr'm Jarvis, 1763); with typed transcript, 1 p., 2 copies, of the N.H. letter. (Box-folder 1:42)
      Requests that when it is published soon, a copy of his A Wonder Book for Girls and Boys be sent to each friend specified, including Longfellow, O.W. Holmes, W. Irving, and others, and seven copies to Z. Burchmore, Jr., for distribution. Enquires about proofs and the preface for Tales (The Snow-Image). #6249-a.
    - Nath[anie]l Hawthorne to W.D. Ticknor, 1851 November 3, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l., tipped to a leaf of heavier paper also bearing a clipped autograph dealer's description; with typed transcript, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:43)
      Sends his preface for the tales (The Snow-Image) and enquires about the manuscript of Major Molineaux, instructing that the "imperfect copy" be returned to him for rewriting if the complete one is not found. Requests $100 dollars for upcoming travel. #6249-a.
    - Nath[anie]l Hawthorne to "Dear Sir" [John Sartain], 1851 December 4, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l. folded. (Box-folder 1:44)
      Discusses length of and price for a story under consideration for his correspondent's magazine. Declines to contribute stories regularly, due to the time and work they take, and notes that this one he wrote while waiting to leave Lenox. #6249-d.
    - Nath[anie]l Hawthorne to G[eorge] P. Putnam, 1852 April 14, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l.; with typed transcript, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:45)
      Discusses Putnam's interest in a drawing of his "home," that he has lived in seven since his marriage ten years before and will soon move into the eighth, in Concord, and of that Sophia may be able to do an appropriate drawing. #6249-b.
    - Nath[anie]l Hawthorne to [J.T.] Fields, 1852 May 3, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. folded; with typed transcript (partial), 1 p. (Box-folder 1:46)
      Emphasizes how much he misses Fields, personally and for his work, such as the novel he has just finished (The Blithedale Romance), which Whipple is reading. Discusses the difficulty of getting fair payment from English publishers and asks that Fields approach several. Encourages his seeing Grace Greenwood while in London and his visiting Concord to see the new Hawthorne home. Mentions corresponding with Barry Cornwall and Miss [Mary Russell] Mitford. #6249-a.
    - Sophia Hawthorne to George [P. Putnam], 1852 June 30, ALS, 3 pp. on 2 l., the second addressed on the verso; with typed transcript, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:47)
      Explains that she has begun work for him on a sketch of their house, the Wayside (later than intended due to caring for the baby, teaching the older children, and other work), that Emerson's house is too overgrown with shrubbery to sketch, and that she can not sketch the Old Manse as he asked. #6249-b.
    - Sophia Hawthorne to George [P. Putnam], 1852 June 3, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l., addressed on the verso; with typed transcript, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:48)
      Later the same day sends a drawing she had hoped to redo but despairs of finding the time and suggests that his staff artist make adjustments, mentions the hope of getting an "end view" of Emerson's house and possibly something of the Old Manse. #6249-b.
    - Nath[anie]l Hawthorne to "Dear Sir" [G.P. Putnam], 1852 July 1, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. folded; with typed transcript, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:49)
      Uncertain whether the requested leaf of manuscript should be from one of his existing works or something new, he sends both a leaf of The Blithedale Romance and something written "for the purpose," also comments on Sophia's drawing of the house and describes its color. #6249-b.
    - Nath[anie]l Hawthorne to C.H. Peirce, 1852 November 4, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l. folded; with typed transcript, 1 p. with 2 copies. (Box-folder 1:50)
      Declines an invitation to give a lecture before the Rochester Athenaeum on the grounds that he does no public speaking. #6249-e.
    - Nath[anie]l Hawthorne to Charles Corbit, 1853 January 27, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l. folded; with typed transcript, 1 p. (Box-folder 2:1)
      Declines to provide a note or letter written him by "General Pierce," for which he has had many requests. #6249-a.
    - Nath[anie]l Hawthorne to "Dear F." [Farley], 7 February 1853, ALS, [p. 2 only of 2], 1 p. on 1 leaf with several words clipped from upper left corner; with a photocopy of the first page of the letter, housed in the Berg Collection, NYPL, 1 l. (Box-folder 2:2)
      Describes to this friend how he likes his house and grounds in Concord and his proximity to Mr. Emerson and other friends, but has not gotten out on the river or fished it. Asks after Farley's son and wife and reports his own children are well. #6249-d.
    - Nath[anie]l Hawthorne to Robert Carter, 1853 March 19, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. folded; with 2 typed transcripts, 2 pp. and 1 p. (Box-folder 2:3)
      Has just finished work for a new book [Tanglewood Tales]; considers the effect of including actual friends as characters in his writings as well as developing a Bacchanalian character. #6249-a.
    - Nath[anie]l Hawthorne to [Hackley], 1853 June 22, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. inlaid in a heavier sheet. (Box-folder 2:4)
      Sends thanks for loan of a note, which gave him some insight about its writer; discusses plans for his 6 July steamer crossing to England where he would take up his duties as Pierce's appointed consul at Liverpool. #6249-a.
    - Nath[anie]l Hawthorne to F[rancis] Bennoch, 1853 August 23, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l., with typed transcript, 1 p., and typed notes on the full series of letters to Bennoch, continued into 1862, 1 p. with 1 carbon copy. (Box-folder 2:5)
      Forwards a letter written to Bennoch by Mr. [James T.] Fields and sent through N.H., who speculates that it may concern a matter unknown to Fields's partner [William D.] Ticknor. #6249-a.
    - Nath[anie]l Hawthorne to [George N.?] Sanders, 1853 November 16, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. folded. (Box-folder 2:6)
      Pleads the case of an older Irishman, referred to him by Sanders, who is seeking work in Liverpool, something N.H. cannot offer, but presses Sanders himself to find something for him in London. #6249-d.
    - Nath[anie]l Hawthorne to George N. Sanders, 1854 February 1, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. folded. (Box-folder 2:7)